本字幕由诸神字幕组（kamigami.org）制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:aimie king  翻译:念白白 poopy   校对:木落 时间轴:wcaster
Kishuu Province, Wakayama Castle
吉宗公より　姫様がこの紀州に入られるという知らせ
Shogun Yoshimune has sent
a message that the Princess
is on her way to Kishuu.
姫様が井戸に
She's going to the well?
藩主様　藩主様
My lord!
My lord...
It's dangerous to be outside, my lord.
藩主様　そこは危のうございます
よい　ここでよい
It's fine.
This is where I must be.
安心しろ　紀州の者共
Be not afraid, people of Kishuu.
我らは争いに来たのではない
We have not come to fight.
我が名は　真田幸村
My name is Sanada Yukimura.
紀州藩主　徳川宗直殿に会いに来た
I have come to meet Kishuu's lord,
Tokugawa Munenao.
さ　真田　幸村
Y-You are Yukimura?
百年前の亡霊が　虫人となって蘇ったか
A ghost from a century past,
reappearing as an Insect-man?
The Cool Guy in Glasses
Lectures on Right and Wrong
【クールなメガネのОＸ講座】
East Sea Road, Enshuu Province
はあ　富士のお山がもうあんな遠くに
Look how far Mt. Fuji is...
あ　お付きの方
Miss!
虫奉行様のお付きの方　お待ちください
Servant of the Insect Magistrate,
please wait!
Uh, where are we going?
一体　どこに向かってるんですか
このままだと江戸からどんどん離れてしまいます
We're getting far from Edo.
自分には　江戸でのお勤めがあるんですが
I have my job in Edo...
これもお勤めじゃ
This is part of your job.
Part of it...
お勤め
江戸へはしばらく帰れぬ
You cannot return to Edo for a while.
月島　お主はこれから妾のお供として紀州藩に参るのじゃ
Tsukishima,
you will accompany me to Kishuu Province.
な　なんと
Wh-What?!
自分が紀州藩へ
I'm going to Kishuu Province?!
って　紀州藩ってどこですか
Um, where is Kishuu Province?
You'll know when you arrive.
来ればわかる
Then, why are we going to Kishuu Province?
それで　なぜ此度は紀州藩へ行くのですか
Wrong.
バツです
Huh?
ただのお供に知る権利などありません
A mere attendant has no right to know.
Um, miss...
あの　お付きの方
Is that the Insect Magistrate?
もしかして　あのお方が虫奉行様なのですか
虫奉行
The Insect Magistrate?
はい
Yes...
あの風格あるお姿は　自分が思い描いていた虫奉行様とは違いますが
His style isn't quite what I had
expected of the Magistrate.
ひょっとしたらと思いまして
But I thought I should I ask.
あれは虫奉行ではない
That is not the Magistrate.
江戸南町奉行　大岡越前守忠相
He is Oooka Echizen no Kamitadasuke,
of the Edo Southtown Magistrate's.
数々の都市政策に携わるキレ者
A brilliant man, heavily involved in city policy.
江戸随一の頭脳を持つ者と言われておる
He's said to be the smartest man in Edo.
I can hear you,
聞こえてますよ　お付きの方
miss...
それは済まなかった
I apologize.
お気になさらずに
Do not allow it to concern you.
私はただあなたの道中をお護りするというお上の命に従うのみです
I merely obey the Shogun's orders
to protect you on your journey.
I apologize for not introducing myself!
ご挨拶が遅くなりました
自分は虫奉行所市中お見廻り組同心　月島仁兵衛と申します
I am Tsukishima Jinbei, of the
Insect Magistrate City Patrol!
拝見させてもらいます
Let me see it.
See what?
拝見
い　あの　何をですか
U-Uh, what do you mean?
行きましょう　時間の無駄です
Let's go.
We're wasting time.
わしが　徳川宗直だ
I am Tokugawa Munenao.
Let's hear your demands.
要件を聴こう
What are you after, Sanada?
何が狙いぞ　真田とやら
船が欲しい
I desire a ship.
人間千人が乗ろうと一切動じぬ巨大な船を作ってほしいのだ
I want you to create a huge ship, one that can carry
a thousand humans without difficulty.
巨大な船
A huge ship?
この紀州藩には　質のよい木材があり　またそれを扱う人材がそろっている
Kishuu has excellent wood
and men who know how to work it.
これを見よう
Look at this.
これは曾て　織田信長公が考案した戦船を元に
This is a modified version of the warship
Oda Nobunaga originally proposed.
この幸村が自ら手を加えたものだ
I personally altered the plans.
幕府の水軍が何千何万と現れようと　物ともせずに薙ぎ払う無敵の軍艦
An invincible battleship that could easily defeat
tens of thousands of Shogunate ships...
この船さえ渡せば　我らは速やかにここを立ち退く
If you give me this ship,
we will leave at once.
貴様らの目的はそれだけなのか
That is all you want?
それだけ　妙なことを言うな
All?
A strange question...
こんな辺鄙な城　他に用事などあろうはずがない
What else could we want from
a frontier castle like this?
そうであろう　宗直殿
Correct, Lord Munenao?
造船を手配する
I shall order the ship.
それで紀州の民の殺生をやめてくれるのだな
And in exchange, you will not
harm the people of Kishuu?
この真田幸村　己が発した言葉を違えたことはない
I, Sanada Yukimura, have never
gone back on my word.
これから紀州はどうなる
What will happen to Kishuu?
む　宗直様
M-Munenao-sama?
Be at ease, men!
皆の者　安心せい
我が紀州は安泰なり
Kishuu is safe!
Iseya Inn
It took a while, but we reached an inn.
遅くはなったが　無事宿に着いたな
明日も楽しみだ
I look forward to tomorrow.
バツです　月島殿
That's wrong, Tsukishima-dono.
Oh?
はい　大岡殿　自分はただ歩いてただけですけど
Oooka-dono, I was just walking...
No matter what path you travel,
たとえどんなあぜ道であろうとも
一方の武士ならば左側を歩くべきです
a samurai should walk on the left.
侍とすれ違う時　鞘当てをしてしまいますからね
If you should pass another samurai that way,
your swords could collide.
鞘尻がぶつかると殺傷を引き起こす喧嘩になることもあります
If that happened, it could start
a fight that would end lives.
Right!
はい
A true samurai should avoid
unnecessary combat.
武士の道を極めるなら無用な斬り合いはしてはならない
気をつける事です
Be careful.
わかりました　大岡殿
Understood, Oooka-dono!
Are you in trouble?
お困りでしょう
I shall help you!
不肖この月島仁兵衛　お手伝いさせていただきます
Thank you, samurai!
ありがとうございます　お侍様
You saved us...
助かりました
いえ　礼には及びません
No need for thanks.
Wrong.
バツです
Why?
なぜですか
What if those two had attacked the servant?
もしあの親子がお付きの方に襲いかかったら　どうするのですか
But those two could never—
ですが　あの親子に限って
油断は禁物です
You cannot lower your guard.
武士は敷居を跨げば七人の敵がいるという言葉があります
They say that if a samurai rolls up the carpet,
he'll find seven enemies waiting beneath.
いついかなる時もお付き方の身を案じていなければなりません
No matter the circumstance, you must
consider the servant's safety first.
はい　わかりました
Yes, sir! Understood!
ヤッホー
Yahoo!
バツです
Wrong.
お魚
Fishies!
バツです
Wrong.
揺れるぅー
It's shaking...
大バツです
Very wrong!
月島殿　やはりあなたはこのお勤めにふさわしくない
Tsukishima-dono!
As I thought, you are not the
right person for this job.
な　なんと
Wh-What?
大岡
Oooka...
申し訳ありません　お付きの方
I'm sorry, miss.
しかしこの道中はお忍び　なによりとても重要性の高いお勤め
But this mission is covert,
and it is a critical one.
お供が好き勝手をし　万が一なという事は絶対あってはなりません
It must not fail because of
your follower's indiscretion.
これ以上バツが出るようでしたら　即刻江戸にお帰り願いたい
If he does anything else wrong,
I'd like him to return to Edo immediately.
As a samurai, I would be greatly shamed
紀州藩を目前にして　お役御免とはなんたる武士の恥
to be sent back when we've
nearly reached Kishuu...
承知致しました　大岡殿
Understood, Oooka-dono!
必ずや期待に応えてみせます
I shall do all I can to meet your expectations!
What a mess...
困ったなー
どうすればいいんだ
What should we do?
Tsukishima-dono...
月島殿
あぁ　はい
R-Right!
駄目だ　ここは通せん
No, no one's going through.
あの　それはなぜですか
Why is that?
理由などない　とっとと帰れ
No reason!
Now get lost!
ですが　紀州藩に入るための手形やほかに必要なものを全て用意してあります
But we have the note to allow us into Kishuu,
and everything else that is required!
駄目だ　さっさと立ち去れ
No... Begone!
失礼
Excuse me.
関所役人を呼んでいただこう
Call the master of this place.
私は江戸南町奉行所　大岡忠相
I am Oooka Tadasuke,
of the Edo Southtown Magistrate's.
我らの事は徳川宗直公より秘密裏にお達しが来ているはず
A secret letter from Shogun Tokugawa
regarding our arrival should
have already come.
速やかに通さねば　関所の役人の者達全員　腹を切る事になりますよ
If you do not let us through at once,
everyone at this station will be forced
to cut open their stomachs.
黙れ　黙れ
Shut up!
我らは　藩主宗直様より　何人とも通すなとの命が来ているのだ
We've been ordered by the
lord of this province
Munenao-sama, to let none pass!
Munenao-sama said that?
宗直様から
This is the right thing to do.
これでよい
No matter how the Shogun may punish me,
吉宗公よりどのような処罰を受けようとも
真田幸村がいるこの紀州に　姫様を入れるわけにはいかぬ
I cannot allow the Princess here,
so long as Sanada Yukimura is in Kishuu...
どうやら紀州藩内部で思わしくないことが起きているようですね
It appears something unpleasant
is happening in Kishuu.
さようか
Indeed.
他に紀州藩に入る道はないんですか
Is there any other way into Kishuu?
お　おお　大岡殿　本当にこの崖を越えれば紀州に入れるのですか
O-Oooka-dono, will crossing this
cliff really take us into Kishuu?
Yes.
I'm amazed you knew this.
よくご存知でしたね
不測の事態に備え　前に調べるのは当然の事
Naturally...
You must be prepared for any contingency.
しかし　なんと厳しい道
But this is extremely dangerous...
お付きの方　本当にお一人で大丈夫ですか
Are you really okay on your own, miss?
自分で良ければ　手を貸しますよ
I'll help you if you'd like.
気持ちはありがたいが　この程度の事心配無用であっ
I appreciate the sentiment,
but you needn't worry about—
Ah!
...me.
あ　お付きの方
Miss!
Yes, I'm fine.
うむ　助かった
I'm glad you're safe...
ご無事で何よりです
月島　こんな事をせずとも良い
Tsukishima, you do not have to do this.
妾は一人で大丈夫だ
I'm all right on my own.
No, you're not!
いいえ　ダメです
Please be quiet and hang on tightly!
お付きの方は　黙ってしっかりつかまっていてください
どうかされましたか
Is something wrong?
It's nothing.
なんでもない　ただ
It's only that you're more like you
お主はお主らしい方が　お主らしいな
when you act like yourself.
H-Huh?
あれが第二の関所ですか
Is that the second gate?
そうです
Yes.
それでこれからどうなさるのですか
So what do we do now?
和歌山城へ迎えます
We head for Wakayama Castle.
Wakayama Castle?
和歌山城？
うむ　そこにわらわの必要な物がある
Yes, what I need lies there.
Who's there?
誰だ
何だ　貴様ら
What are you doing here?
まずい
Uh-oh...
どっから入ってきた
We're getting out of here.
離れます
Everyone! Intruders!
皆の者　曲者が侵入したぞ
であい　であい
Get them!
こっちに行ったぞ
They went this way!
そこまでだ　貴様ら
That's far enough!
次から次へと
They just keep coming.
こうなったら
We have no choice.
He drew his sword!
こやつ　刀を抜きおった
Does he want to fight?
やるのか
Tsukishima.
月島
月島殿　無益ですぞ
Tsukishima-dono...
This is pointless.
Don't worry...
どうかご安心を
恋川殿に教えてもらいました
Koikawa-dono taught me this.
この木は　爪楊枝
This tree is a mere toothpick!
Did we lose them?
逃したか
Find them!
探せ　探せ
この辺りにいるのは間違いない
They must be nearby!
There are a lot of them.
大人数ですね
このまま　夜まで待ちましょう
Let us wait until night.
We'll cross the second post in the dark.
闇に紛れて　第二の関所を越えるのです
Wh-Who are you?
何だ　お主は
貴様も曲者の仲間か
Are you with the intruders?!
何とか言え
Say something...
構わぬ　引っ立てよう
Forget it!
Grab him!
Impertinent.
うるさくそうろう
何　なんて…
H-How—
Be quiet.
静かに
Humans are as useless as expected.
やはり人間は使えぬでざそうろう
関所一つ守れぬとは
They cannot protect a single post?
My name is Nedzu Jinpachi,
of the Ten Crucifix Insects.
拙者の名は　真田十傑虫が一人　根津甚八
Ten Crucifix Insects
Nedzu Jinpachi
Show yourselves, rats.
姿を現せ　ネズミ共
そこにいるのは分かっておりそうろう
I can sense your presence.
許しません
You won't get away with this...
I won't let you!
断じて許せません
Wrong.
バツです　このお勤め中の私情は禁物ですぞ　月島殿
You must not let your feelings
interfere with your task, Tsukishima-dono.
この場は退くのです
We must run.
Oooka-dono, these are not
my feelings talking!
大岡殿　これは私情ではありません
あのものは　人の命を奪うこの世の悪
He kills people! He is evil!
成敗しなければ人の道に外れます
Unless I defeat him, I would
be neglecting my duty!
Tsukishima-dono,
月島殿　お付の方にもしものことがあったら　どうするのですか
what if something were to
happen to the servant?
ネズミ共　成敗いたしそうろう
Rats, I will kill you.
You bastard, you killed them all!
貴様　よくも皆さんを
大岡殿　自分がこの蟲人を足止めします
Oooka-dono, I shall slow this Insect-man.
Insect-man?
蟲人
先にお付の方と紀州の中へ
Take the servant and get to Kishuu!
なんということ　この場でお勤めを差し置くなど　大バツです
You cannot abandon your task here.
That is very wrong.
かまわぬ　月島
I do not mind, Tsukishima.
お主がしたいようにすればよい
Do as you will.
お付の方
Miss...
何も気にするな　そやつを成敗せよ
Have no fear...
Defeat him.
わらわが許す
I allow it!
承知
Very well!
I will not let you escape.
逃がしいたさずそうろう
Neck... Head... Side.
首　頭　脇
何と鋭く
His strikes are so swift,
そして的確に急所ばかりを狙ってくる
and they aim only for vital points.
こいつ　恐ろしく戦い慣れしている
He is a master of combat.
あの猿飛佐助というものより　遥かに強い
Far stronger than Sarutobi Sasuke!
It's been a long time.
久しい　実に久しい
A very long time...
蟲の身になっており
I never thought I'd see someone,
まさか これほど拙者の剣と渡り合える者が現れようとは
since I became an insect,
who could match my blade so well.
なかなかどうして　楽しませてくれそうろう
You will entertain me a good deal.
ふ　ふざけるな
Shut up!
なっ　腕が伸びた
His arms extended!
完全に遊ばれている
He's only playing with me...
ネズミ　その程度の腕でそうろうか
Is that all you've got, rat?
I still have more tricks.
拙者にはまだまだ奥の手がこれありそうろう
I don't understand.
解せません
Shogun Yoshimune ordered me to protect
道中あなたを守り付き従うようにと吉宗様からの命があり
and obey you on our journey,
一切口を挟まぬつもりでしたが
so I had not planned to say anything.
But why did you choose that
man to accompany you?
なぜ此度の勤めのお供に あの者を選んだのですか
注意力は散漫で　警戒心もなく　勤めに私情を持ち込む
He doesn't focus or pay attention.
He allows his feelings to interfere with his task.
武士としてあまりに幼稚な立ち居振る舞いが目立ちます
As a samurai, he acts like a child.
バツです　大バツです
This is wrong. Very wrong.
Take this...
これを受けそうろう
しもべ共　参らせそうろう
Go, my servants!
Crane Wing Egg Formation!
Crane Wing Egg Formation
鶴翼卵の陣
背中の卵が
Eggs from his back?
He is not an appropriate choice to protect you.
あなたをお守りするお供として　あまりに相応しくない
Why did you select him, Princess?
姫様　何ゆえあの者
He was the most suited to the task.
都合がよいのだ
はぁ？
月島はわらわの正体を勘違いしている
Tsukishima is mistaken as to my identity.
And I wished to make some memories, as well.
それにわらわは思い出を作っておきたくてな
姫様　どうぞこちらへ
This way, Princess.
I, Oooka Tadasuke, do not
understand your feelings.
この大岡忠相　やはり姫様の思いは分かりません
But that does not change my obedience.
だけど　あなた様に付き従うことに変わりはありません
月島　門は開いた
Tsukishima, the gate is open!
Come quickly!
早く参れ
Right!
はい
I will not let you escape.
逃がしいたさずそうろう
This is the end!
これにて終わりそうろう
三刀流では逃げ場がありません
There's no way to block all three attacks!
Tsukishima!
月島
He caught one in his teeth?
歯で受け止めた
受け止める　これが皆さんの無念
Take this!
This is for the people you killed.
Tsukishima-style: Mt. Fuji Hammer!
月島流　富嶽鉄槌割り
I have failed!
不覚
このネズミ　なかなかに
Well done, rat.
Tsukishima-style: Mt. Fuji Strike!
月島流　富嶽突き
Curse you.
おのれ
I've let the rats escape...
ネズミ共　取り逃がした
なかなか順調のようですね　親方様
It seems to be coming along well, my lord.
Indeed.
So, Jinpachi, is what you say true?
それで　甚八
その話はまことか
Yes, three rats have entered Kishuu.
はっ　ネズミが三匹紀州に
その者達は 我らの存在を知っているようで
And they seemed to know of us.
They called us "Insect-men."
我らのことを「蟲人」　と呼んでござそうろう
They call us Insect-men?
我らは「蟲人」か
呼び名など気にもしなかったが　面白い
I never put any thought into our name,
but that's amusing.
By the way, Jinpachi...
ときに　甚八
お主はいつまで　頭を下げているのだ
How long will you bow your head?
I failed at the pass.
拙者は関所の監視で不適は起こしそうろう
I cannot possibly face you.
親方様に顔向けなど　とてもできぬそうろう
根津は相変わらず堅苦しくてかなわん
Nedzu is always so stiff.
当藩への侵入者がこやつらのことを「蟲人」といったとな
So those who entered my province
referred to them as Insect-men?
その呼称を使うのは　極一握りの者しかいない
Only a few use that name.
つまり姫がこの紀州藩に入ったということか
In other words, the Princess has entered Kishuu?
Munenao-dono, how will you atone for this?
宗直殿　この落とし前　どうつける
落とし前とは…
Atone?
我らがここに滞在していることは絶対に秘密
Our presence in Kishuu is a secret.
何人たりとも関所を通すなと命じた
I told you to let none pass.
This means the promise
you made has been broken,
これは約束が反故されたのを意味し
我らは紀州藩の民全てを殺さねばならん
and we must kill all the citizens of Kishuu.
That's insane!
なんと無茶苦茶な
Then bring me the heads of these rats...
ならば　貴様らがそのネズミ共の首をもってこい
Use every single citizen of Kishuu
今すぐ紀州藩　全ての民を使い
to bring us the corpses of the rats
that called us the Insect-men!
そのネズミの屍を　我らの前に差し出せ
Next Time
Miss, I can't wait to rest after our
long journey. How about you?
お付の方　長旅で疲れた体を癒したいですね
Indeed.
そうじゃな
Ideally, at a hot spring!
癒すといえば温泉です
そうじゃな
Indeed.
ちょうどよいところに混浴が…
And there's a mixed-gender one right here!
大バツです
Very wrong.
Next time, on Mushibugyou:
次回蟲奉行「真田幸村の罠！お尋ね者包囲網！！」
Sanada Yukimura's Trap.
Sanada Yukimura's Trap! Caught in a Net!!
Caught in a Net.